David Hamburg MD Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
David Hamburg MD Papers
1996 - 2011
This collection documents David Hamburg's work in the prevention of deadly conflict, mass violence, and genocide between 1996 and 2011. The collection has 4 series: United Nations, European Union, Scholars and World Leaders, and Written work.
1.67 linear feet (4 boxes)
Hamburg, David A., 1925-2019
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
2011.0001
Dr. Hamburg’s work during his presidency of the Carnegie Corporation is available at Columbia University.
Gift of David Hamburg, 2011.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
David Allen Hamburg (1925-2019), DeWitt Wallace Distinguished Scholar at Weill Cornell Medical College, had a long history of leadership in the research, medical and psychiatric fields. Among other roles, he served as Professor and Chairman of Psychiatry at Stanford University (1961-1976), President of the Institute of Medicine, National Academy of Sciences (1975-1980), Professor of Health Policy at Harvard University (1980-1983) and President then Chairman of the Board of the American Association for the Advancement of Sciences (1984-1986). He was President of the Carnegie Corporation of New York from 1982 until 1997, after which he joined the Department of Psychiatry at Cornell in 1998.
Hamburg devoted the later part of his career to the prevention of deadly conflict, mass violence, and genocide, particularly through his pioneering work as co-chairman of the Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict, as chairman of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on Prevention of Genocide at the United Nations, as chairman of a parallel committee to the Secretary General of the European Union, and through his work with numerous world leaders, renowned scholars, and non-governmental and academic institutions. He accomplished much of this work during his time at Cornell. The collection documents his work in conflict prevention between 1996 and 2011.
Hamburg, David A., 1925-2019; United Nations; Annan, Kofi A. (Kofi Atta); Ki-moon, Ban; Boutros-Ghali, Boutros, 1922-2016; Méndez, Juan E.; Deng, Francis Mading, 1938-; Tutu, Desmond; Solana, Javier; European Union; Genocide Prevention; Obama, Barack; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Clinton, Hillary Rodham; Rice, Condoleezza, 1954-; Allison, Graham T.; De Klerk, F. W. (Frederik Willem); Bush, George W. (George Walker), 1946-
The collection includes Dr. Hamburg’s correspondence, meeting materials, written notes, and other materials accumulated between 1996 and 2011 in the following four categories: United Nations (1996-2011), European Union (2002-2011), Scholars and World Leaders (1996-2011), and Written work (1996-2010). The electronic archive contains all of the materials donated to Cornell. The hard copy archive primarily includes original correspondence with world leaders, key meeting materials, written notes, and books/reports.
United Nations: Hamburg played a key advisory role at the United Nations in multiple departments, most notably in the Executive Offices of three Secretaries-General. Examples of his work at the UN included: facilitating linkages between the global scientific community and the UN (1996-2001); establishing an international policy framework and network on “Health as a Bridge for Peace” based out of the World Health Organization (1997-2006); serving as advisor to the UN High Commissioner for Refugees (1997-2001); serving on the Board of Trustees for the UN Institute for Training and Research (1998-2009); and, on Kofi Annan’s request, creating a strong network of advisers to launch the University for Peace (UPEACE) (2000-2001). Through his leadership as advisor to Secretaries-General Kofi Annan and Ban Ki-moon (1997-2010), Hamburg facilitated the appointment of the Special Adviser to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide beginning in 2004; the establishment of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide which he chaired (2005-2010); and the strengthening of the Office of the Special Adviser on the Prevention of Genocide beginning in 2006. The United Nations folder of the archive contains materials from 1996-2011 in the following eight categories: Secretary-General Kofi Annan and his Core Staff (1997-2007), Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon and his Core Staff (2006-2010), Secretary-General Boutros-Boutros Ghali (post tenure), Special Adviser Juan Mendez (2004-2008), Special Adviser Francis Deng (2007-2011), Advisory Committee to the SG on Prevention of Genocide (2005-2011), Related United Nations Initiatives (1996-2006), Research and Reports on the UN and Preventing Deadly Conflict.
European Union: Hamburg’s activities in the European Union during his later years also pivoted around the prevention of deadly conflict and genocide, and the collection includes materials from 2003-2010. Parallel to his Advisory Committee at the UN, Dr. Hamburg also chaired an advisory committee to the Secretary General of the Council of the European Union, Javier Solana, in order to establish an international center on the prevention of genocide based out of the EU. By 2008, plans were underway to establish the center in Hungary. Between 2007 and 2010, Hamburg also became involved with the European Union Institute for Security Studies (EUISS), both as an advisor and as an active participant in meetings and conferences. The European Union section of the collection spans from 2003 to 2010 and includes materials in the following five categories, and significant initiatives, meetings, individuals, and highlights covered in each category are detailed below: Secretary General Javier Solana and Core Staff (2005-2010), Steering Committee on Preventing Genocide (2005-2011), Establishment of International Center in Hungary (2008-2010), Related EU Initiatives (2003-2010), EU Key Documents (2007-2010).
Scholars and World Leaders: Dr. Hamburg’s wide-reaching leadership and scholarly activities positioned him well to form professional and personal relationships with international leaders in government, academia, and the field of human rights. His close relationship with Desmond Tutu is well-documented in the Advisory Committee folder of the United Nations section. Hamburg’s correspondence and working relationship with the following individuals are included in this section, and correspondence and related materials are grouped chronologically: 1996-2005 Condoleezza Rice and George W. Bush, 2001-2010 Hillary R. Clinton, 2002-2009 Jimmy and Rosalynn Carter, 2004 Graham Allison, 2005-2006 FW De Klerk, 2005-2011 John Packer and Max Van der Stoel, 2008-2009 Barack Obama, 2009 Office of War Crimes Issues.
Written work: The hard copy archive includes the Final Report of the Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict and Hamburg’s recent books on prevention of deadly conflict and violence: No More Killing Fields: Preventing Deadly Conflict (2002); Learning to Live Together: Preventing Hatred and Violence in Child and Adolescent Development (2004); and Preventing Genocide: Practical Steps toward Early Detection and Effective Action (2010). Additionally, there is an annotated script of Hamburg’s documentary based on his most recent book. The electronic archive includes written work in the following categories: 2007-2010 Documentary on Preventing Genocide; 2008 Press; 2008-2010 PMV Overview Material; 2009-2010 Autobiographical Statements re: Work on PMV; and Lectures and Key Documents. The latter file includes a major proposal submitted to the co-chairs of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, John Kerry and Richard Lugar, to establish a series of hearings on “Preventing Mass Violence as an Organizing Principle of American Foreign Policy.”
- United Nations
  - Secretary-General Kofi Annan and Core Staff, 1997 - 2007; Original correspondence between Hamburg and Secretary-General Annan is grouped by year, along with key reports and notes. The Annan files span from 1997 through 2006. Core staff members grouped into the Kofi Annan file include (in alphabetical order): Mark Malloch Brown, Deputy Secretary-General; Michael Doyle, Special Adviser to the Secretary-General; Ibrahim Gambari, Under-Secretary-General for Political Affairs; Angela Kane, Assistant Secretary-General for Political Affairs; Tapio Kanninen, Chief of Policy Planning at the Department of Political Affairs; Edward Mortimer, Director of Communications in the Executive Office; Gillian Sorensen, Assistant Secretary-General for External Relations; Maurice Strong, Executive Coordinator for UN Reform; John Ruggie, Assistant Secretary-General for Strategic Planning; and Danilo Türk, Assistant Secretary-General for Political Affairs. Hamburg worked with these individuals in different capacities to implement the prevention agenda at the UN. Hamburg’s work with Kofi Annan and his staff with respect to prevention of deadly conflict and other mass violence can be outlined by several major landmarks (with corresponding documents in the archive). The Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict (CCPDC) was completed in 1997, and on 6/25/1997, Hamburg and CCPDC’s Executive Director, Jane Holl, co-wrote a letter to Annan outlining key findings of the Commission and emphasizing that “Prevention is a compelling substantive theme for UN Reform.” Kofi Annan responded positively to the CCPDC’s charge, and the Final Report of the Commission was presented at the United Nations by Kofi Annan on 2/05/1998. Subsequently, Hamburg gave a presentation at a Security Council Retreat which gave special attention to the prevention of deadly conflict as outlined by the CCPDC (6/04-6/05, 1999). Hamburg played a key role in the drafting, launching, and implementation of Annan’s landmark report on the Prevention of Armed Conflict (PAC Report) (6/07/2001) and the related call by the Secretary-General for responses by UN Departments and Agencies (5/15/2002). On 10/29/2001, Hamburg sent Annan a section of his book, No More Killing Fields, which described the background and significance of the PAC Report. Hamburg also had involvement in subsequent reports to PAC: Implementing the Millennium Declaration (9/06/2001); the General Assembly Resolution on the Prevention of Armed Conflict (7/03/2003); the Interim Report on the Prevention of Armed Conflict (9/12/2003); the Report of the High Level Panel on Threats, Challenges and Change (2004); and the Progress Report of the Prevention of Armed Conflict (7/18/2006). Related correspondence with core staff is filed with the reports. In 2001, Hamburg was invited to be part of a Strategic Planning Meeting with the Secretary-General and a panel of experts and advisers to help identify and shape the priorities of Annan’s second term as Secretary-General. The meeting took place from 1/11-1/12, 2002 (the 2001 Strategic Planning invitation from Michael Doyle is grouped with these meeting materials). Conflict prevention was identified as a priority. Between 2001 and 2004, Hamburg played a leadership role in organizing a “core group” of individuals focused on the implementation of the recommendations outlined by the Secretary-General’s PAC Report. Also included as part of the Kofi Annan folder, the core group consisted of Ragnar Angeby, Melanie Greenberg, Jane Holl, Tom Leney, and Connie Peck. Hamburg’s memo to this group on 4/04/2002 and his related memo to Annan on 7/12/2002 provide a useful picture of the suggestions of that group and the important steps being taken at the UN as a whole to accomplish the prevention mission. Staff members of the Executive Office and the Department of Political Affairs, listed in the first paragraph of this section, were closely involved in the logistics of implementation, particularly through the vehicle of the Interdepartmental Resource Group (also referred to as the “InterAgency Resource Group”) on Conflict Prevention, chaired by Danilo Turk and working primarily in 2004 (see materials dated 3/29/2004 and 10/21/2004) and the Chief Executive Board High-Level Committee on Programmes. Danilo Turk and Tapio Kanninen were key players in these groups, and the archive contains numerous items of correspondence and written documents by them. Hamburg continually reported on the progress of these groups to the Secretary-General, most notably in his letter/memo dated 7/12/2002. This memo gives a comprehensive overview of the work being done and Hamburg’s suggestions regarding the implementation of the prevention mission. Hamburg’s notes and assembled documents in the 2003 folder, DAH Implementation Docs and Notes provides a glimpse of the meetings, efforts, and considerations that Hamburg was engrossed in at that time with respect to the implementation of prevention at the UN. The particularly significant outcome of Hamburg’s work with Annan and these key individuals was the 2004 establishment of the OSAPG, initially headed by Juan Mendez, and the 2006 creation of Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide, chaired by Hamburg. Correspondence with Kofi Annan dated 3/04/2004, 3/16/2004, and 4/22/2004 indicate the progress being made toward the appointment of a Special Adviser. Annan’s remarks to the Human Rights Commission in the press release dated 7/04/2004 affirms his commitment to the prevention of armed conflict, to developing an early warning system on genocide, and to taking swift and decisive action based on these indicators. Moreover, he announces his creation of the post, Special Adviser on the Prevention of Genocide. Correspondence between 7/22/2004 and 12/30/2004 and Hamburg’s 7/2005 notes indicate the appointment of Juan Mendez as Special Adviser and Hamburg’s advice regarding the position. On 7/07/2005, Hamburg recommended the appointment of an Advisory Committee, which was then discussed in correspondence and achieved in early 2006 (see Annan’s invitation letters to the proposed members on 2/14/2006). Hamburg’s efforts with the Special Adviser and Advisory Committee are outlined more fully in sections 1D-1F. (Box 1)
  - Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon and Core Staff, 2006 - 2010; Original correspondence between Hamburg and Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon is grouped by year, along with key reports and notes, and span from 2006 through 2010. Core staff members grouped into the Ban Ki-moon file include (in alphabetical order): Jan Eliasson, former General Assembly President and Special Envoy on Darfur; Vijay Nambiar, Chef de Cabinet to the Secretary-General; Robert Orr, Assistant Secretary-General for Policy Coordination and Strategic Planning; B. Lynn Pascoe, Under-Secretary General for Political Affairs (replacing Ibrahim Gambari); and Kim Won-soo, Deputy Chef de Cabinet to the Secretary-General. At the time of Ban’s appointment, Hamburg was chairman of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide and Juan Mendez was Special Adviser to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide. However, the OSAPG did not yet have a full-time Special Adviser or a permanent staff. Hamburg, Mendez, and the Advisory Committee met and worked with high-level UN staff members between 2006 and 2009 to make the OSAPG more robust. When Ban took office as the new Secretary-General in December of 2006, he vowed to make genocide prevention a priority of his tenure (see press dated 1/2007 as well as 4/09/2007). Hamburg met with the Secretary-General on 1/19/2007, and his notes indicate that they discussed Hamburg’s personal history in conflict prevention beginning with the Cuban Missile Crisis; the existing assets for genocide prevention at the UN including the Advisory Committee, the DPA and the OHCHR; and the priorities for fuller implementation of the genocide prevention agenda, most notably through the appointment of a full-time Special Adviser on genocide prevention. Following the meeting, Hamburg worked with Juan Mendez and his committee to develop a list of potential candidates for this role, which was submitted to the Secretary-General in 2/2007. Upon the appointment of B. Lynn Pascoe as Under-Secretary-General for Political Affairs, Hamburg took the opportunity to write a substantive letter on 3/09/2007 describing his own background in conflict prevention and proposal for future meeting and collaboration. Francis Deng was appointed as the first full-time Special Adviser in May of 2007 (see press release dated 5/29/2007). Correspondence and notes related to Francis Deng as Special Adviser can be found in sections 1E-1F. The theme of Hamburg’s work with Ban, his core staff, the Special Adviser, and the Advisory Committee during the period between 2007 and 2009 is the overall strengthening of the OSAPG. In early 2007, there was much discussion on the title of the OSAPG (see Hamburg letter to Vijay Nambiar dated 2/05/2007). In 5/2007, Francis Deng was appointed as Special Adviser, and Hamburg and Deng met with the Chef de Cabinet and Deputy Chef de Cabinet on 6/27/2007 to discuss the activities of the OSAPG, in particular the implementation of the “Responsibility to Protect” (R2P) principle through the appointment of a Special Adviser on R2P appointed as part of Deng’s unit (see Hamburg’s correspondence with Deng dated 6/28/2007). A meeting of the Advisory Committee was planned for the fall. A report of that meeting was submitted to the Secretary-General and his senior staff on 10/31/2007, in which the question of R2P was discussed further. On 8/21/2008, Hamburg submitted a letter to the Secretary-General indicating his intention to resign as Chairman of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide. The letter also makes suggestions for future duration, composition, and chairmanship of the committee. Subsequent correspondence with Ban and his staff relates to Hamburg’s last meeting as Chairman of the Advisory Committee on 10/27/2008, whose report was submitted to the SG on 2/02/2009. Hamburg’s letter to Ban dated 6/03/2009 provides a useful overview of the achievements and strengthening of the OSAPG with Deng as Special Adviser and reiterates Hamburg’s proposals for the next phase of the Advisory Committee. In the 8/21 and 6/03/2009 letters, Hamburg proposes that Desmond Tutu or Amartya Sen would be excellent candidates to replace him as chairman of the Advisory Committee. (Box 1)
  - Secretary-General Boutros-Boutros Ghali, 2001 - 2008; Original correspondence between Hamburg and Secretary-General Boutros Boutros-Ghali is grouped by year and spans from 2001-2008, taking place after Boutros-Ghali’s tenure as Secretary-General (1992-1996). The correspondence includes Boutros-Ghali’s request to publish Hamburg’s text, “The Foundation for a Renewed United Nations” (9/21/2001); discussion of September 11th (Ibid); plans to meet in Paris (2/26/2003) and discussion of Hamburg’s work in prevention (Ibid). The hard copy file also contains letters between 2003 and 2008 (missing from the electronic archive) with requests from Boutros-Ghali for Hamburg’s assistance in establishing his foundation. Correspondence and materials presenting Hamburg’s relationship with Boutros-Ghali during his tenure as Secretary-General are not included in this archive, but an excerpt from Hamburg’s book, No More Killing Fields describes their work together as follows: "In my first conversation with Boutros Boutros-Ghali a short while after he became Secretary-General, we discussed the prevention approach. He was exceedingly thoughtful and stimulating. When Cyrus Vance and I organized the Commission, Boutros Ghali was helpful in many ways. We in turn tried to be helpful to him, particularly in his leadership in preparing three key documents: An Agenda for Peace; An Agenda for Development; and An Agenda for Democratization. All these pointed in the direction of prevention, bringing the UN back to the basic orientation formulated by Franklin Roosevelt and others at its inception." Note: the excerpt from which this quote is taken was sent by Hamburg to Kofi Annan on 10/29/2001 and described the significance of Annan’s 2001 Report on the Prevention of Armed Conflict. (Box 1)
  - Special Adviser Juan Mendez, 2004 - 2008; Juan Mendez, human rights attorney and former Argentinian political prisoner, was appointed as the first Special Adviser to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide in 2004. Relevant correspondence and meeting materials span from 2004-2006. Following the appointment of the second Special Adviser in 2006, Juan Mendez continued to serve as a member of the Advisory Committee to the Secretary-General on the Prevention of Genocide and correspondence with Mendez continues through 2008. Staff members to Mendez while he was Special Adviser include Suzanne Ndedi-Penda, Andres Salazar, and Ekkehard Strauss. Archived documents indicate the following landmarks and highlights with respect to Juan Mendez’ leadership as Special Adviser. Mendez was appointed as Special Adviser in 2004 (7/12 and 7/13, 2004) and Mendez announced his appointment to the International Center for Transitional Justice (ICTJ), where he had just begun as president (7/02-7/14, 2004). The archive indicates that there was continual discussion about the part-time nature of Mendez’ leadership as Special Adviser during his ICTJ presidency (see 7/2005 DAH notes for Annan re Mendez). On 8/05/04 an informal brainstorming session was held to assist Mendez in “thinking through his initial strategy, methodology, and overall approach” (see related meeting materials). In August 2005, Hamburg and Mendez discussed possible candidates to serve on the Advisory Committee (see correspondence dated 8/15/2005, 12/20/2005 and 1/10/2006). Mendez and Hamburg sent an initial memo to this committee on 3/08/2006 and began planning for the first meeting of the AC on 6/19-6/20, 2006 (materials and correspondence in Advisory Committee folder). The committee met again in September 2006 (materials in Advisory Committee folder) and a meeting with Civil Society representatives was held on 12/14/2006 to discuss how “interested NGOs” could “best support the office of the SASPG.” On 11/15/2006, Andres Salazar reported to Dr. Hamburg on Mendez’ advocacy with the Security Council. The primary theme of correspondence with Mendez in 2007 is the effort to appoint a full-time Special Adviser, culminating in the appointment of Francis Deng in May (see correspondence dated 5/29/2007). Mendez continued to serve on the Advisory Committee following Deng’s appointment. (Box 1)